Space,
فضاء,
we all know what it looks like.
جميعنا نعلم كيف يبدو.
We've been surrounded by images of space
نحن محاطون بصور للفضاء
our whole lives,
طوال حياتنا,
from the speculative images
بداية من الصور التأملية
of science fiction
للخيال العلمي
to the inspirational visions of artists
إلى التصوير ملهم للفنانين
to the increasingly beautiful pictures
إلى الصور التي تزداد جمالاً
made possible by complex technologies.
بفضل تكنولوجيات معقدة.
But whilst we have
ولكن إمتلاكنا
an overwhelmingly vivid
هذا الكم الهائل من
visual understanding of space,
من الفهم البصري الحي للفضاء,
we have no sense of what space sounds like.
لم يعطينا اي فكرة عن ما هو صوت الكون.
And indeed, most people associate space with silence.
في الحقيقة, معظم الناس يربطون الفضاء بالسكون والصمت.
But the story of how
ولكن قصة كيف
we came to understand the universe
وصلنا إلى فهم الكون
is just as much a story of listening
هي مجرد بقدر فهمنا لقصة الاستماع
as it is by looking.
والنظر أيضاً.
And yet despite this,
ولكن على الرغم من هذا،
hardly any of us have ever heard space.
يصعب على اي منا سماع صوت الفضاء.
How many of you here
كم واحد منكم سمع
could describe the sound
ويستطيع وصف الصوت
of a single planet or star?
الناتج من نجم واحد او كوكب؟
Well in case you've ever wondered,
لذا, في حال كنت تتساءل,
this is what the Sun sounds like.
هذا هو صوت الشمس.
(Static)
(ساكن)
(Crackling)
(قرقعة)
This is the planet Jupiter.
هذا هو كوكب المشتري.
(Soft crackling)
(قرقعة ناعمة)
And this is the space probe Cassini
وهذا هو صوت مسبار كسيني
pirouetting through the ice rings of Saturn.
يتراقص داخل حلقات كوكب زحل الثلجية.
(Crackling)
(قرقعة)
This is a a highly condensed clump
وهذي مجموعة كثيفة للغاية
of neutral matter,
من مواد طبيعية,
spinning in the distant universe.
تدور في الكون البعيد.
(Tapping)
(طرق)
So my artistic practice
إذاً, ممارساتي الفنية
is all about listening
جميعها تدور حول الإستماع
to the weird and wonderful noises
للضوضاء الغريبة ورائعة
emitted by the magnificent celestial objects
المنبعثة من الأجسام السماوية عظيمة
that make up our universe.
التي تكون الكون
And you may wonder,
وقد تتساءل,
how do we know what these sounds are?
كيف لنا أن أن نعرف ما هي هذه الأصوات؟
How can we tell the difference
كيف لنا أن نعرف الفرق
between the sound of the Sun
بين صوت الشمس
and the sound of a pulsar?
وصوت النجم؟
Well the answer
حسننا, الإجابة هي
is the science of radio astronomy.
أنه علم الفلك الراديوي.
Radio astronomers
علم الفلك الراديوي
study radio waves from space
يدرس موجات الراديو في الفضاء
using sensitive antennas and receivers,
مستخدماً هوائيات ومستقبلات حساسة,
which give them precise information
والتي بدورها تعطي معلومات دقيقة
about what an astronomical object is
عن ماهية هذا الجسم الفلكي
and where it is in our night sky.
وأين يقع في سماءنا المظلمة.
And just like the signals
وكما في الإشارات
that we send and receive here on Earth,
التي نرسلها ونستقبلها هنا على الأرض,
we can convert these transmissions into sound
يمكننا تحويل هذه الرسائل والبث إلى صوت
using simple analog techniques.
مستخدمين تقنتيات تناظرية بسيطة.
And therefore, it's through listening
وبالتالي، فإنه من خلال الاستماع
that we've come to uncover
إستطعنا كشف
some of the universe's most important secrets --
بعض أهم أسرار الكون --
its scale, what it's made of
مثل الحجم, ومما يتكون
and even how old it is.
وحتى عمره الزمني.
So today, I'm going to tell you a short story
اليوم, سوف أخبركم قصة قصيرة
of the history of the universe through listening.
عن تاريخ الكون عبر الإستماع.
It's punctuated
ويتخللها
by three quick anecdotes,
ثلاث حكايات سريعة,
which show how accidental encounters
والتي تبين كيف أن مصادفات عرضية
with strange noises
مع ضوضاء غريبة
gave us some of the most important information
تعطينا بعض من اهم المعلومات
we have about space.
التي نملكها عن الكون.
Now this story doesn't start
في الحقيقة هذه القصة ليست مبنية
with vast telescopes
على تلسكوبات واسعة وعديدة
or futuristic spacecraft,
او مركبات فضائية مستقبلية,
but a rather more humble technology --
بل على وسيلة أكثر تواضعاً --
and in fact, the very medium
في الحقيقة, هي الوسيلة
which gave us the telecommunications revolution
التي أعطتنا ثورة الإتصالات السلكية واللاسلكية
that we're all part of today:
والتي تجمعنا جميعاً اليوم:
the telephone.
الهاتف.
It's 1876, it's in Boston,
إنه في عام 1876 في بوستن,
and this is Alexander Graham Bell
وهذا هو ألكساندر غراهام بيل
who was working with Thomas Watson
الذي كان يعمل مع تومس واتسون
on the invention of the telephone.
في إختراع التلفون.
A key part of their technical set up
مفتاح التقنية الاساسي لهذه التقنية
was a half-mile long length of wire,
كان يكمن في سلك طوله نصف ميل,
which was thrown across the rooftops
والذي أُلقي به عبر اسطح
of several houses in Boston.
لعدة منازل في بوستن.
The line carried the telephone signals
هذا الخط قام بنقل إشارات التلفون
that would later make Bell a household name.
والتي في وقت لاحق جعلت بيل إسماً معروفاً.
But like any long length of charged wire,
ولكن كأي سلك طويل مشحون,
it also inadvertently became
أصبح من غير قصد
an antenna.
هوائي.
Thomas Watson
تومس واتسون
spent hours listening
قضا ساعات في الإستماع
to the strange crackles and hisses
لفحيح وقرقعة غريبة
and chirps and whistles
وتغريد وصفير
that his accidental antenna detected.
إلتقطها بشكل مصادف الهوائي.
Now you have to remember,
الآن يجب عليك أن تتذكر,
this is 10 years before
هذا كان قبل 10 سنوات
Heinrich Hertz proved the existence of radio waves --
من إثبات هاينريش هيرتز لوجود موجات الراديو --
15 years before Nikola Tesla's four-tuned circuit --
قبل 15 سنه من ضبط دوائر الأربعة لـ نيكولا تيسلا --
nearly 20 years before Marconi's first broadcast.
قبل تقريبا 20 سنة من أول بث لـ ماركوني.
So Thomas Watson wasn't listening to us.
لذا, تومس واتسون لم يكن يستمع إلينا.
We didn't have the technology
لم تكن لدينا التقنية
to transmit.
للبث والنقل.
So what were these strange noises?
إذاً, ماذا كانت تلك الضوضاء الغريبة؟
Watson was in fact listening
في الحقيقة, كان واتسون يستمع
to very low-frequency radio emissions
إلى موجات راديو قليلة التردد
caused by nature.
سببتها الطبيعة.
Some of the crackles and pops were lightning,
بعض القرقعات والفرقعات كانت من البرق,
but the eerie whistles
ولكن الصفير الغريب
and curiously melodious chirps
وإقاعات التغريد المثيرة
had a rather more exotic origin.
كانت منشأها أكثر غرابة.
Using the very first telephone,
بإستخدام أول هاتف,
Watson was in fact
واتسون كان في الحقيقة
dialed into the heavens.
يتصل بالسماء.
As he correctly guessed,
وكما توقع بشكل صحيح,
some of these sounds were caused
بعض هذه الاصوات كان سببها
by activity on the surface of the Sun.
النشاط على سطح الشمس.
It was a solar wind
كانت الرياح الشمسية
interacting with our ionosphere
تتفاعل مع الغلاف الجوي الخاص بالارض
that he was listening to --
وهذا ما كان يستمع إليه --
a phenomena which we can see
ظاهره يمكن أن نراها
at the extreme northern and southern latitudes of our planet
في اطراف خطوط الطول والعرض في كوكبنا
as the aurora.
كالشفق.
So whilst inventing the technology
في زمن هذه الإختراعات التقنية
that would usher in the telecommunications revolution,
والتي من شأنها أن تثير ثورة في الإتصالات السلكية واللاسلكية,
Watson had discovered
واتسون إكتشف
that the star at the center of our solar system
أن النجم الذي في مركز نظامنا الشمي
emitted powerful radio waves.
يعطي موجات راديو قوية.
He had accidentally been the first person
لقد كان بالمصادفة الشخص الأول
to tune in to them.
الذي يضبط موجتهم.
Fast-forward 50 years,
50 سنة سريعة إلى الأمام,
and Bell and Watson's technology
تقنية بيل وواتسون
has completely transformed
غيرت بالكامل
global communications.
التواصل العالمي.
But going from slinging some wire
ولكن الإنتقال من قذف بعض الأسلاك
across rooftops in Boston
عبر الأسطح في بوستن
to laying thousands and thousands of miles of cable
إلى زرع الألف الأميل من الكيابل
on the Atlantic Ocean seabed
عبر قاع المحيط الأطلسي
is no easy matter.
ليس بالأمر السهل.
And so before long,
قبل مدة طويلة,
Bell were looking to new technologies
كان بيل يبحث عن تقنيات جديدة
to optimize their revolution.
لتحسين ثورتهم.
Radio could carry sound without wires.
يمكن للراديو أن ينقل الأصوات بدون أسلاك.
But the medium is lossy --
ولكن الوسط الناقل ضعيف --
it's subject to a lot of noise and interference.
إنه يخضع لكثير من الضجيج والتشويش.
So Bell employed an engineer
لذلك, وظف بيل مهندس
to study those noises,
ليدرس هذه الضوضاء,
to try and find out where they came from,
لمحاولة معرفة مصدرها,
with a view towards building
بهدف بناء
the perfect hardware codec, which would get rid of them
أجهزة ترميزية مثالية يمكنها التخلص من هذه الضوضاء,
so they could think about using radio
لذا, أمكنهم التفكير في إستخدام الراديو
for the purposes of telephony.
لغرض الهاتف.
Most of the noises
أغلب الضوضاء
that the engineer, Karl Jansky, investigated
التي بحث عنها المهندس كارل جانسكي
were fairly prosaic in origin.
كان مصدرها ضعيفاً.
They turned out to be lightning
تبين انها من البرق
or sources of electrical power.
او وجود مصدر كهربائي.
But there was one persistent noise
ولكن كان هناك ضوضاء واحدة مستمرة
that Jansky couldn't identify,
والتي لم يتعرف عليها جانسكي,
and it seemed to appear
والتي كانت على ما يبدو تظهر
in his radio headset
في سماعة جهاز الراديو الخاص به
four minutes earlier each day.
اربعة دقائق في وقت أبكر كل اليوم.
Now any astronomer will tell you,
أي فلكي سوف يخبركم,
this is the telltale sign
أن هذه علامة منبهة
of something that doesn't originate from Earth.
لشيء مصدره ليس الأرض.
Jansky had made a historic discovery,
لقد إكتشف جانسكي إكتشافاً تاريخياً,
that celestial objects could emit radio waves
وهو أن الأجسام السماوية يمكن أن تصدر موجات راديو
as well as light waves.
فضلاً عن موجات الضوء.
Fifty years on
خمسون سنة مضت
from Watson's accidental encounter with the Sun,
على لقاء واتسون العرضي مع الشمس,
Jansky's careful listening
وإستماع جانسكي الدقيق
ushered in a new age of space exploration:
يبدأ عصر جديد لإستكشاف الفضاء:
the radio astronomy age.
عصر علم الفلك الراديوي.
Over the next few years,
وعلى مدى السنوات القليلة القادمة,
astronomers connected up their antennas to loudspeakers
سوف يربط الفلكيون هوائياتهم بمكبرات الصوت
and learned about our radio sky,
ليتعرفوا على إذاعة السماء,
about Jupiter and the Sun,
ليدرسوا كوكب المشتري والشمس,
by listening.
عن طريق الإستماع.
Let's jump ahead again.
دعونا نقفز إلى الأمام مرة أخرى.
It's 1964,
إنه عام 1964,
and we're back at Bell Labs.
وها نحن نعود إلى مختبرات بيل.
And once again,
ومرة أخرى,
two scientists have got a problem with noise.
عالمان كانت لديهما مشكلة مع الضوضاء.
Arno Penzias and Robert Wilson
ارون بنزيز و روبرت ويلسون
were using the horn antenna
كانا يستخدمان هوائيا قمعيا
at Bell's Holmdel laboratory
في مختبر بيل
to study the Milky Way
لدراسة مجرة الدرب اللبني (درب التبانة)
with extraordinary precision.
مع الدقة الاستثنائية.
They were really listening
لقد كانوا يستمعون فعلاً
to the galaxy in high fidelity.
إلى المجرة بدقة عالية.
There was a glitch in their soundtrack.
كان هناك خلل في الصوت الخاصة بهم.
A mysterious persistent noise
ضوضاء مستمرة وغامضة
was disrupting their research.
كانت تعيق بحثهم.
It was in the microwave range,
لقد كانت على نطاق الموجات الدقيقة,
and it appeared to be coming
وكانت على ما يبدو اّتية
from all directions simultaneously.
من جميع الإتجاهات في وقت واحد.
Now this didn't make any sense,
الآن, هذا ليس له أي معنى.
and like any reasonable engineer or scientist,
وكمثل اي مهندس او عالم واقعي,
they assumed that the problem must be the technology itself,
افترضوا أن المشكلة تكمن في التكنولوجيا في حد ذاتها،
it must be the dish.
يجب أن يكون الطبق هو المشكلة.
There were pigeons roosting in the dish.
كانت هناك طيور حمام معششة في الطبق.
And so perhaps once they cleaned up the pigeon droppings,
وما إن يتم تنظيف الطبق من روث الحمام,
get the disk kind of operational again,
سوف يعود الطبق للعمل مرة أخرى,
normal operations would resume.
وتعود معه العمليات الطبيعية.
But the noise didn't disappear.
ولكن الضوضاء لم تختفي.
The mysterious noise
الضجيج الغامض
that Penzias and Wilson were listening to
الذي كان يستمع إليه بنزيز و ويلسون
turned out to be the oldest and most significant sound
تبين أنه الصوت الأقدم والأهم
that anyone had ever heard.
يمكن لأي شخص أن يستمع إليه.
It was cosmic radiation
لقد كان الإشعاع الكوني
left over from the very birth of the universe.
الذي وُجِدَ منذ ولادة الكون.
This was the first experimental evidence
لقد كان هذا أول دليل من تجربة
that the Big Bang existed
على وجود الإنفجار العظيم
and the universe was born at a precise moment
وان الكون ولد في لحظة دقيقة
some 14.7 billion years ago.
قبل ما يقارب 14,7 مليار سنة.
So our story ends
والآن, قصتنا إنتهت
at the beginning --
في البداية --
the beginning of all things, the Big Bang.
بداية كل الأشياء, هي الإنفجار العظيم.
This is the noise that Penzias and Wilson heard --
هذه هي الضوضاء التي سمعها بنزيز و ويلسون --
the oldest sound that you're ever going to hear,
أقدم صوت يمكن أن تسمعه في حياتك,
the cosmic microwave background radiation
خلفية الإشعاع الكوني
left over from the Big Bang.
الذي نتج عن الإنفجار العظيم.
(Fuzz)
(زئير)
Thanks.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)